this is from the end Guccione Khayyam
suitor called
walking walking walking and it says if a
sensual thoughts were full of ill world
cruelty arises while walking and if you
tolerate it and do not abandon it then
you are devoid of ethics and moral of
shame constantly lazy and lacking energy
while walking
he goes on whether walking standing
sitting or lying down one who thinks bad
thoughts connected with household life
has entered upon the wrong path
infatuated by the elusive things such a
person cannot be free the one who has
his thoughts calmed and delights in
stilling of thought such a person
see there's a lot of the walking
meditation not there people like to do
but it's they focus on the with feeling
of their feet on the sand quite sure
they think here is and that's in
a walk from this point to that point how
many steps thirty stay same for any body
posture at the setting
well when the Buddha says he's upon the
wrong ha means he's going down the wrong
direction that's what it means in the
more in the more most accurate manner so
going down the wrong path it's basically
attending to things wrong that means
going down the wrong direction of you of
your efforts so even the ones who are
making efforts and that's exactly the
example you gave when when you're doing
walking meditation mostly today people
again they're after your after an
experience of peace or some some sort of
some sort of firm
factual thereafter experience of peace
or some sort of experience of some
novelty the other butt
the other butt
how many people would use the meditation
to reflect upon the nature of the
thoughts yet that's all the sort of
talked about as anything that really
matters is to not entertain the
unwholesome and to calculate the whole
so whether you're sitting walking lying
down understanding whether you're
talking about your long
people but yes unfortunately today you get this
but yes unfortunately today you get this
like a moss loop retreat centers and
zone and then you get taught like
documentation you observe the soles of
your feet and you try to like be being
as present as possible and catch the
moment it's on all that is nothing other
than just a focusing practice on a
particular aspect of your body on a
particular basically type of perception
of touch that's it and it can be so it
can it can produce a release for people
because most of the most of the rest -
they are the rest of the time they spend
they spend their the day in unmindful
state are very busy very engaged and
they're just focusing on one particular
thing and refusing to give attention to
everything else seems like a way to go
because it provides you with a degree of
peace but that peace is only relative to
your lifestyle beforehand that peace is
not the measure of your understanding
and wisdom that comes if you do the
Dhamma correctly and it's it's no hard
thing to see that just see when you when
you're out of the retreat how much of
your composure you can keep when you go
back to your daily life there are other
things dealing with things whether you
still be able to remain impenetrable to
the unwholesome States as you walk in
sitting lying down or standing
and most people want that's where they
come back for retreats for long and
retreats the longer it reads more
attacks to treat all that a little bit
and I say if I focus on my feet walking
on the sand right then I don't think any
central thoughts well that's the thing
that's the earth where you focus is not
the root to the problem the root of the
problem is not understanding the nature
of unwholesome and because of that being
subject to it because you don't know how
even unwittingly you entertain it you
feel it you feed it
which means you end up acting out of it
so think of unwholesome thoughts are a
problem then proliferating unwholesome
thoughts are a further problem so what
happens when people do the focus in
practice they would focus on one
particular thing and refuse to give
attention to everything else including
the problem the problem of unwholesome
so then they can feel like yeah this is
really working and I mean I'm not saying
this absolutely like no benefit
whatsoever but I'm saying that benefit
is only relative for those who work or
or distracted most of the other time
distracted with duty with family with
sensuality or just video views in some
cases so the point is to recognize that
even like yeah I'm not giving attention
to the problem can help you but that's
not solving the problem that's just
managing it dealing with it temporarily
and that's exactly the point you can
practice and further this type of
focusing meditation only such a retreat
settings you can't sustain that out in
the world or you can't sustain that if
you have to climb up and down the
mountain every single day for Pinder but
for five kilometres in rain or whatever
else you can try but you gonna burn out
very soon as you see many many many
cases that didn't work we both kind of
witness but the monks will go in the
great seclusion focused on some sort of
technique to do it and then just after a
week you can't handle it you need you need
you can't handle it you need you need
something you need some reference point
because okay now you stopped attending
you're just focusing on one thing but
that's it that's that that's a wall
that's a dead end
so the only benefit you were getting
before from your meditation practice
wasn't because of what you were focusing
on is because of what you were not
focusing on which was the unwholesome
you were not focusing on unwholesome
there was the peace you were getting now
you arrived and not focusing on a
wholesome because you're focusing on
something else which sooner or later
environment will prevent you to do so or
you're just gonna run out of the of the
most obvious inspiration to do so and
then what you're gonna do you're just
back in the same unwholesome which
remain intact because you you haven't
been understanding and discerning it
resolving it you've been ignoring it -
marching the soles of your feet -
watching the tip of your nose and so on
so that's what I mean
nobody denies that people can experience
peaceful feelings when they do focusing
meditation but the point here is that
won't result in approaching the problem
it's only covering it up can only
approve the problem if you if you have
to if you start looking at it for what
it is directly and that's exactly where
the code but part of the suta you read
this talks about
so that's what you reppin is the work is
not about me doing walking meditation
for eight hours a day or focusing on my
nostrils all the time
the work is recognizing whether the mind
is affected by ill-will affected by
greed affected by delusion affected by
unwholesome state and then not
entertaining that doesn't matter whether
I'm walking sitting lying down or
standing yeah the posture is your
reference point that you don't need to
interfere with if you know where the
problem is and the problem is mind
affected by I'm also so indeed sometimes
when it's just too much to deal yeah
just ignore it just don't pay any
attention to it until it comes down so
that you can go back to it and deal with
it but adopting a practice of just
constantly not looking at the problem
and focusing on something else as a way
of release from the problem it's not
gonna solve anything there's absolutely
no discernment there no wisdom
understanding because you're not looking
at it distraction it's a form of
distraction that's why that's what the
Buddha did say Maggie garrets similarly
says not being free not being free from
sensuality this summit of the Brahmins
they premeditate miss meditate over
meditate under meditate but they don't
meditate and it gives the simile says
they are like like an owl hunting for a
mouse or a cat waiting to pounce on fish
similar basically similes of preying
upon something of focusing on one moment
where you act where you catch it where
you grab it and he said that's a good
that's meditating with sensuality that's
looking completely down the wrong path
so that's again just imagine yourself
trained upon something you're waiting
for a donor the mouse to come out of
this hole
you mustn't skip a beat because he might
escape you and see whether that's
different from where people try to not
skip a beat when they're observing the
soles of their feet or not skip a beat
when they're focusing on the nostrils or
the belly movement or whatever you end
up calculating the same attitude of
preying upon something trying upon
something that you clearly think has
valuable it's going to resolve all your
problems catching this mouse will fix
all my problems catching these perfect
moments that come and go in front of me
would purify my mind but that's a
complete he said people who meditate
meditate with sensuality that's why the
premeditated miss meditate over Mary
Daly under meditate and so on but I
don't meditate so you walking
thought cruelty arises
elevated yeah which means you don't like
sort of cruelty arises means there is
your work then for you in its entirety
sort of quilty that's the problem
nothing else so you don't you don't stop
everything you'll be doing you don't you
just give it all up because I will never
I don't want ever to have such thoughts
again you can't do that because well
it's not up to you those thoughts will
be presented themselves so do you in
order for for you to not be victim of
those presentations of ill will or
sensuality you need to understand how
you engage with it and you won't
understand the habits of your engagement
with those thoughts while they are
simultaneously present there if you're
so response to that is look away it's
just look away
just ignore it just just consider my
breath consider my breath stop think
about it stop thinking about it and on
top of that you're gonna wind yourself
up much more because thinking that you
must stop thinking is another thought
then you're thinking in order to not
think so that way it becomes so intense
and sort of a present as you have
you recognize the thought of cruelty but
they just stops in a way that's enough
very often sometimes your recognition
might not be clear enough so then you
need to endure it you have to recognize
where by how much of the thought arises
on its own and then you have to
recognize whether where the line is
where if you cross then it's you doing
it you entertaining it you getting
involved with you trying to get rid of
it all of those are ways of fueling the
thought including you actively trying to
ignore it why would like there is a 30
man I must focus on my source of my
faith must why is your trying to avoid
the reason thought in your mind if you
think you must not have and by trying to
avoid things that are disagreeable to
you what are you doing you're doing
exactly the thing you shouldn't be doing
acting out of craving in regard to how
you're feeling there is the unpleasant
feeling get rid of it get rid of it get
rid of it there is the pleasant feeling
I must have longer Thomas Ravenal
this is exactly that's not you doing the
crew thought presented himself
it's a cruel thought it's not mine this
is it it's like somebody comes right
here in front of your door and this is a
public space your cooties yours they
can't come in but have every right to
stand in front I could but if you feel
affected by that that's a new so if you
come out of your couch and start to
chase them well now you actually went
into something that's not your domain
not your ownership and trying to control
it which that means you left to tell
attended and then other things can come
in with you everywhere in no way and the
same in the same manner the thing cannot
come in whatever thought is unless you
invited it unless you drag it in and
that's what happens with sensuality
either sensuality as in like agreeable
desire or disagreeable something want to
get rid of it just comes in front of you
but if it's agreeable you were the one
who brings it in if he's disagreeable
you are who goes out and tries to chase
it either way you overstepped your
boundaries and because of that you're
subjected to it that's why you're
affected by
so that's what is that another suitor
winner but it did say while he was still
unenlightened Bodhisattva when he was in
them it's called fear and dread
but he said he was staying in his in
these frightening forest in groves with
wild animals and then he would be doing
walking meditation at night and he said
if there is a he would hear some sound
or something or have a frightening
thought he wouldn't change what he was
doing which is working minute he
wouldn't stop walking he wouldn't stop
walking until he dispels that
unwholesome state of mind and then he
might change the posture in the same
manner whether he was seated standing
sitting or lying down he wouldn't change
the posture before unless he first
removed the unwholesome state then
arisen when you remove the unwholesome
state by not acting out of it by not
trying to get rid of it by not trying to
prolong it
and that exactly means I wouldn't change
the posture until this state is
dispelled because if if the unwholesome
state came up and now she stopped
walking and done something else means he
acted out of it and that's already a way
of fueling whether you acted out of it
in her forms of trying to prolong it as
an unwholesome state of sensuality or
trying to deny it get rid of it as
quickly as possible as in unwholesome
state of ill-will or fear or anything on
disagreeable so the point is you
recognize and then how much of it arises
on its own and then you don't either add
to it or take away from it and when it
subsides then you change the both
so if you do that long enough if you do
that long enough any no matter how
subtle ways of fueling down wholesome
states of your mind you've been
entertaining they will all fade because
you just you're uprooting it left and
right bit by bit by bit I mean you can
bit by bit by bit I mean you can
approach things but it takes time for
them to sort of wither and die but one
thing for sure they'll never wither it
out and you certainly never recruited
them if you keep looking elsewhere if
you keep focusing on the nostrils for
the sake of avoiding the thought and not
having to think about anything and not
having to experience this pleasure if
you keep focusing on the soles of your
feet because you're trying to catch a
perfect moment and develop this ultimate
peace they will never be disturbed then
the non disturbance doesn't come from
not experiencing disturbing things non
disturbance comes from not being
disturbed by the disturbing things so
for as long as you concern with the
disturbing things not with your response
in regard to disturbing things you're
looking in the wrong direction you are
down the wrong path
Spencer could work to study
yeah yeah playing games some something to do
yeah playing games some something to do
basically we focused on doing things
staring at things perceiving things
observing things but not looking
your attitude behind that the
intentionality behind the motivation
behind the craving behind craving is
always behind it's always in regard to
if you never look in that direction of
that background never gonna see this
again these ideas by being in a
particular posture firstly lower back
straight spine erect using boost le all
this job is preposterous
that doesn't do the work for you but
that is it's a game as you play two
stretches it's a little ritual okay
little motion motions you go through to
create the significance of what you're
about to do because if you just sit down
stare at the wall or look down the hill
and contemplate
why do you suffer when there is a when
you can't fulfill your desires but why
do you suffer when you experience
something disagreeable
why do you suffer when you pair with
things you don't want why do you suffer
when you're separate from things you
want yeah there's not much to it that
you can perform and it's it's for many
people it's it's almost just abstract so
they need something more palpable which
is on a level of sort of mechanical
performance doing things with your body
particular posture particular way of
walking I must then be stepping on the
outsides of my soles of whatever I can't
be walking like this I must walk slowly
I can't walk fast all of that is being
concerned with a particular with a
particular content to your perception
failing to see the nature
certainly failing to recognize enduring
feeling in regard to it yes
athletic meditation sure - well it's all
based as I said it so it all revolves
around trying to perceive trying to
catch preying upon something and that's
why you would have to go through these
specialized motions because if you walk
too fast you can't be catching something
so you must walk slowly to slow down
stand stand and just look at it just
just just grab it as it comes out
recognize it and that's it
and that's nothing else than meditating
with that same sensuality that you're
trying to overcome so if there's no
unwholesome thoughts
if no a wholesome well then you're
either an arrogant or you don't know
what unwholesome thoughts are so you
think they're not arise along they're
fully there it can't be the third option
so you ask yourself am I not have to no
means there are and also stop thoughts
which means I need to look harder or
change change they change the criteria
for what constitutes also so I'm also
thought
peaceful experience it doesn't mean that
it's not a mouse
peaceful experience is unwholesome
if you don't understand it
of course not ultimately I was not also
on the level of arranging sensuality
with manual will but from the point of
view of ultimate complete thoroughly
bration yeah if there is no full
understanding to their degree it's an
awesome let's all going to say the
neutral feeling and the sublime feeling
praised by the wise it's unwholesome if
it's not known and it's wholesome if
it's known constant constant
knowledge
that's the thing there's no constant
knowledge in a sense of all knowing all
the time in every direction that's
impossible knowledge in regard to the reason that's
knowledge in regard to the reason that's
why they will talk about knowledge ever
rising
customer service sure sure
constant knowledge with regard to rising
its other words saying wisdom in regard
to Thomas
in regard to things that manifest
because that's it wisdom States that's
why if you develop wisdom in regard to
nature of things
their wisdom stays there is always
things are always present in one way or
the other which means wisdom with regard
to them it's always present that's
Nibbana fully developed principle like
that is what devours
to be generative wisdom well it's simple
tennis terrorizing so whatever it's
manifested that is wisely understood its
nature has been fully abandoned
disregarded in a sense of no
appropriation or some
because you can't not have things
arising for you
even if you're just locked in some
buried in some cave without any
perceptions still Dunn was already from
you all the time as you thought as
absence of sights absence of sounds
those are real manifested thing things
such so for as long as the five
aggregates are there functioning there
is the five aggregates of phenomena the
five aggregates of manifestation there's
a matter how much of a content within
that you might have or not that's we're
trying to avoid sight sound smell taste
touches the Buddha compare that to blind
in a deaf man not to somebody who's
developing wisdom
of course you avoid you and also you
don't engage with the unwholesome sight
sound smell taste touches you don't
entertained it but that's just replacing
one very and wholesome content with not
unwholesome content but in order to be
free from either you need to fully
understand the nature of that content
and you won't get there just by staring
at the content and expecting content to
tell you what its nature is because that
would mean people could almost
accidentally stumble upon enlightenment
just by staring and suddenly they get it
but you can't you need to develop
another suit in and Goodwin kind
nobody's talking to finally do there
cycles this is
this is
this dumber is for one with few desires
but for one with strong desires
with reference to what
sit this is when a bhikkhu is one is few
this is when a bhikkhu is one is few
desires there's not desire let people
know me to be one with fuses
when he when he is content he does not
design that people who know me to be the
one who's content when he was ordered to
solitude he does not desire that people
know me to be one resource to solitude
when he is energetic design that people
know me to be energetic when he is
mindful he doesn't want people to know
that he's mindful
when he's composed he does not want
people to know that he's composed and
when he is wise he doesn't want people
to know that his voice when he delights
in non-proliferation is my desire
Loie through one who delights
so this dummy is for one this feud is
ice
so not seeking for fame
in a way yes always it's more it's more
fundamental than just the fame he comes
down to let's see all of the things that
would elicit for some things a few
desires solitude mindfulness wisdom
restraint but it's it's almost like a
desire can be also reflexive it doesn't
necessarily need to be focused from the
central content you can be practicing
renunciation in the forest but then on
the reflexive manner you can be well you
can be developing the child on the
country conceit you can be indulging
that so if you really want your practice
to make a difference yourself you need
to you need to practice on both of those
levels so to speak in other words you
need to be mindful of the motivation
behind your practice
so if say you want to go in the in the
remote forest but the motivation behind
it is because so the world will spread
around that you go out to be remote
forests so you'll be yep famous was
simply conceited with the experience
pleasure and account about the knowing
that now that doesn't mean you shouldn't
go to the forest is going to the forest
is still wholesome but when you go to a
forest if you were to forest you make
the effort to reroute that motivation to
not have it rooted in those thoughts of
Fame a conceit but rooted actually in in
practicing the renunciation in the same
sense the Buddha encouraged when you
come down to eating but we can't just
stop eating but if you eat with right
motivation then it's not an awesome if
you don't eat with right motivation then
it's automatically unpause but it
doesn't mean if you cannot eat with
right motivation you must stop eating
no you just must work harder to be able
to reroute the motivate the reasons for
your eating to route them in wholesome
non routine mean unwholesome
so in that sense you recognize firstly
what is it that you're about to do and
then secondly why yes I want to go and
keep older to Tonga's and live in the
forest very good okay why that's why the
Buddha will sometimes say let those who
want to go and live on the route or to
live under you to feel that those won't
eat once a day eat once a day or lead
out on the boat
not everybody must do it because some
people won't be able to help it but do
it out of conceit out of cry out of I
can sit motionless for 10 hours and I
eat only 173 days like Giants they
started out doing each other in the
practices who's gonna go further harder
asceticism but nor it not know second
layer of that reflection I'm talking
about which is focusing on are they
doing these things there's a being right
but then why are they bringing the
unwholesome to decrease and increasing
also know you're just winding you up
stronger and stronger in your desire for
fame or recognition or whatever so yes
asceticism is almost always good but if
you really want to make it beneficial
you have to then look at another step
back and see why you're doing it and
they're not necessarily dismiss it if
you find that it's it's done for wrong
reasons but change the reasons like you
can't change the reasons for unwholesome
actually like sensuality for example or
anger you can say oh I reroute that it
good you can't because those things are
cemented in unwholesome motivation overs
motivation of ignorance lust aversion
which means you must just abandon it but
there are many things such as eating or
or even practicing going to the forest
and so on that you can make a noise or
you can do them wholesome they are not
in themselves 100% defined you can they
can be some people live in a monastery
because they're surrounded by others
they become quite ascetic quite you know
many consciousness is by sitting for
many hours each other but as soon as
they go and live on yourselves
it means they haven't been taking
responsibility from the practice for the
practice from the start they've been
relying on the temple environment other
monks around them that's what kept them
in check which means once you are out of
that setting you just what you're doing
it dissolve in the way even if it's not
explicitly for their acknowledgement you
do it you do it basically not with your
own take taking on responsibility in
yourself but you do it because the
environment everybody does it and if you
don't do it will stand out too much it's
not necessarily a bad way to start if
you recognize it then that's only a
starting point but then adhering to the
environment and never changing it for
the sake of the value of the environment
in itself means how do you know that
how do you know where your motivation is
rooted and on top of it it can't
possibly be good for you being
surrounded by the people even if it's
other mothers as the Buddha said well
actually it's very very close to what
what we're talking about that's what I
mean going to the solitude is always
wholesome in itself then yes you can
make it unwholesome but you can undo
that bit and still go to so logic
there's that that suitable the Buddha
said if a monk lives in the forest and
he's his lazy sleeps all the time thinks
about sensuality but he still stays in
the forest means sooner or later the
mind will come down get used to the
perceptions of the forest and he'll
abandon those unwholesome states so
there is the benefit of the environment
but then counterpart to that monkey is
the monk who lives in a temple
frequented by laypeople
not far from the town of the villages
surrounded by other monks he's not alone
he lived it
even if he's not spending his time
thinking about such a thing even he's
not lazy even if he's not negligent he
will become so because the environment
of the crowd and other people that's
what's going to resolve into it so
that's what I mean sometimes you you can
you can benefit from it initially but
not as a fixed fixed in stone sort of
principle that you must always be with
30 other months or you must always be
like within the within the stone's throw
away from the town or the village
quite the contrary you read the suitors
you know at the hearts empty forests and
tables of the trees but I'm waiting for
yeah you kid people can do that oh I
don't wanna deal in this I'll run into
the forest sure it's done for
unwholesome reasons but if they stay in
that forest they will have to collect
those reasons oh they will leave the
forest in this road so in that sense the
environment does what does direct direct
basically direct you in your practice so
no matter of your restraint and and
intelligence and everything else if you
live surrounded by others constantly you
cannot progress
this tumbler is for one two resorts to
solitude right after one who delights in
the company and you know resorted to
solitude means exactly that the actual
physical solitude doesn't mean going to
your bedroom and closing the door be
like 30 other people around you in the
same dorm or something this is when a
bhikkhu resorted to solitude bhikkhus
bikuni is male they follow his female
those followers kings were ministers and
so on
approaching in each case with a mind that's slant
in each case with a mind that's slant
sloped and he climbs to seclusion
withdraw delighting my pronunciation he
gives he gives him a talk concerned with
dismissing so yeah
so yeah
we're not encouraging or entertaining
them to stand along that we don't want
them there you don't want them I mean
you go even further we like you often
end up hiding not like literally sort of
running under the rock but if you see
that people might see you you avoid
being seen yeah yeah exactly like a deer
and that's what I mean it's not like you
know is that that's whatever the Buddha
commanded a nun doctors they were sewing
the robes to the Catena
and he was just you know monastery full
of monks and many of them were probably
so token as soccer the Grammys which
means relatively accomplished but what
they were doing they were socializing on
account of a noble cause of sewing the
robes for the auspicious species
gathering of the Catena and when the
Buddha came in I thought he was a band
of fishing
it says all we're getting ready we're
showing the ropes and then he just
blasted him work to do stop wasting your
time with these distractions and
basically go to solid shitty practice so
that's what I mean you can you can sort
of say that oh yeah go you went to the
forest or somebody went to forest for
conceited reasons yeah that's fine but
going to the forest is never a bad thing
and sooner or later their reasons will
become clear to them which is the point
when they were all they leave the forest
or leave those reasons and you see that
you see the first hand when new people
come in a day and they leave the teacher
right away because they want to go then
they they're just looking for their
nobody doing and then they spend first
two years going from one place to the
other place to the other place to the
other place feels like they tried it all
and then they destroy or they go
straight into solitude and then don't
really know what they're doing they went
for the wrong reasons and then that
becomes apparent but even then if they
were to stay that solitude well they
might go mad sure but if they don't go
mad and if they don't disrobe those
reasons will they will they'll be forced
to abandon those and also reasons that's
what it would have meant by that Souta
even if he's expense his time
fantasizing about sensuality sleeping
all day long in the forest the mind will
adjust and then stop doing those things
because forest is directly
counterproductive for those things he
infuses to leave the solitude refuses to
disrespect the solitude basically in
terms of his views anything that
contradicts it will be abandoned
the other monkey is the one who is not
constantly thinking about society look
might be quite inspiring and restrained
and everything else but he never leaves
his temple he never leaves his monastery
he never leaves the proximity of people
and I say people I mean lay people a
monkey but he talks too he gives talk
which encourages them to stay right
right well yeah ok that's it that's the
political side of running the
monasteries but no I'm just saying from
the from the practice point of view even
if if you're making loads of effort
toward illustrated everything you do
have to recognize what environment
you're in is most of the day that you
spend easy with other people including
other monks even if you don't talk to
anyone are there other monks and laying people
are there other monks and laying people
around you I don't know eight hours a
day of your waking time and if it is so
means you're not a soldier means you
have a you have a break in your room or
something but that's that like a
minority of your time spent in solitude
while the vast majority is just
surrounded in the crowd with solitude
doing exactly yeah people might call
that suitor well the true solitude is
the one without agree diverse delusion
yes and you'll arrive with that when you
do recognize the validity of the
physical solid shape when you do that I
mean if it's really like not that
important ninety percent of the suitors will not
ninety percent of the suitors will not
be talking about it and again as I said
probably quite a noble Sangha at the
time of our eons and so on put together
sewing the rope and the Buddha
reprimanded for socialising such
ridiculous pointless men let alone how
much more today you would have that when
it's most of the time it's not even for
such a lofty cause of solving the road
it's more like just our washing
spittoons together now we're speaking
the leaves together now we do this
together then we go and meditate
together then we go meditate together we
lay people together then we have group
retreats we can stay in the forest alone
but you must come here it's 30 of us
we'll sit together then we need together
and we'll breakfast together then we do
chose together it's just ok so how many
hours per day you spend together and
then those hours that you don't spend
together where do you spend it in the
toilet well for in your bedroom shower
toilet the shower and toilet work or
your bedroom which is paper wall makes
another bedroom with another person
you're never really alone and that's
what I mean from that point of view you
will only be emulating the ideas of
solitude and so on you're playing in the
sand Oh
so to reiterate even if somebody is in
the solitude avoiding socializing for
unwholesome reasons give them a year or
two those reasons will either have to
change what they believe because the
solitude the not socializing well we'll
make it Clifford
you can't have it both you can't have
those wrong reasons for solitude and
stainless ology
sensuality laziness non diligence and I
wanted to deal with people avoiding
running away basically it's all going to
be highlighted and then you're either
going to give into it and abandon
solitude or the solitude will straighten
all of those knots out to be
because this description of Solitude
here does it just mean beautiful green
it means the actual physical solitude so
this dumber is for one who is content
but for one who is discontent with
reference to what was this said here a
big who is content with any kind of
robes absolute lodgings and medicines
and provisions for the sick
he's content
because not being content
to do that is a major distraction
of course for making roads
yeah for making robes for victim
entertaining the crowds for the sake of
support because you need support from
monastery as if none of those things are related
as if none of those things are related
to you
choices and actions you may
because even getting trying to get more
requisites and unique involves non
solitude well absolutely
yeah well even like like for example
again I'm not talking about the temples
the cultural places where people gather
and do the rituals talking about say say
a monastery which is well at least on
paper where monks go to train and
practice but even that it's like you
shouldn't or you you can't afford to be
to be building it for the sake of some
sort of ideal of having a great
monastery we're gonna be like this like
that it can only be built in response to
the practical need because everything
else is is too much it means everything
else would then result in you having to
maintain certain level of engagement
with a people because you need a certain
threshold of funds to maintain the big
place that you built there was
unnecessary but then that means that
everything else becomes secondary to
that including very often the monks
solitude and practice although we all
have to come and eat together because
our big lay supporters they like to see
that
because if they don't like what they see
as in they don't see any monks they all
went to the goodies they might stop
coming they stop coming they'll stop
making donations if they stop making the
nation's well we can't maintain all
these 20 coaches that we built
unnecessarily so that's what I mean it's
built in response to a practical need it
hopefully with the idea of zero
maintenance in the future you don't want
to rely on having to have 20 months all
the time so you can divide all the
duties and trust that everybody can do
everything so things can stay functional
you build simply
with minimum maintenance and then you
factoring that tomorrow you might be
alone even if now they're ten months
tomorrow you might be alone would you be
able to maintain office so if you can't
you shouldn't be going forward if you
are looking too hard to establish a
place for proper practice but if you're
looking how to establish institution
which is already at tempo even if you
call it the forest monastery well that's
a different that's a different ballgame
but that's that's not something that the
forest monk or somebody wants to
practice the Dharma should be good
we're also been able to
you can get you know get robes arms
flute medicines shelters to sort those
things now well that's it that's all
needed that's something we all agree in
Cooper sampling procedure this is the
basis that I agree to anything over that
is extra anything else over that is
unnecessary in a way but just on a
different but being able to sort a
recording but yes the time to be able to
get those things
be content with the simple simple things
you have been able to organize shelter
for yourself know how to get arms not
too fast know how to deal with your body
when it's sick when ministers to music
not to sew your clothing so much you
don't you know done the needs there are
many people well that's what me say
should be all about like like a teacher
okay you teach them in Dhamma and then
on top of that you literally equip them
so that they can live alone they can
live independent they'll know how to
look after themselves in that basic
survival manner if you live in the
forest you cop to fall you smash your
elbow twist your ankle all have basic
recognition like oh hold on am I sick am
i this and my dad just knowing certain
practical things how to survive pair
that with them understanding didn't you
if you only values it gives you you know
being able to survive by yourself of
course gives you the confidence
well content and that's oh and another
thing is ultimately the Dhamma is that
which makes you content even with even
if you don't have the basic requisite
you need it doesn't threaten you exist n
shil you get sick prospect of severe
illness maybe death
you don't go distraught if you've been
practicing Dhamma you won't be able to
be destroyed
yeah sure you you seek out the medicine
but not at all cost and you could see
that there were cases of monks who spend
twenty thirty years in the forest in the
jungle and then they got sick and like
they needed to stay in the hospital for
the sake of basically staying alive and
even that that's not something they
wants to do didn't want to stay in
hospital the bare minimum just to be
repaired and they went back into a
forest because that's which that's what
you value that's what you got used to
but many people today act out of the
life is the greatest game nothing else
is worth doing if it sort of even
exposes a bit of a bit of risk to it I
mean you can live in your lay life like
that that's fine but there's a month
that's kind of living doctor let alone
spending your time worrying about your
future building a monk's hospital and
then what I mean it's nice if white
people do it for whatever purpose but if
you're doing it out of your own
existential concern or what I'm gonna do
when I get old if I get sick well you
should have thought about it when you
haven't been practicing because I heard
cannot possibly worry about those things
well even other gamma goodness it can
worry about maybe the disorder but I can
worry about those things the same extent
but even for people who are for example
lived outdoors
you know survivals yes even they to
extinct oh no don't worry about old age
because then they'd be surviving by
themselves : I've said there's many
examples of people living out in the
woods like non this area except you not
necessarily monks or religious people
just in general and and the air you see
it's quite it's quite a feat and it's
fun inspiring to see that level of
Independence even in
completely again following Buddhist
teaching or whatever but just live
simply remotely gruffly and he's
perfectly fine and even he's in fine
he's fine it's still not not that not
not the reason not the cause for giving
you up and running back into the crowd
where people who look after you because
again it's the life is not gonna last
forever even if you live 100 years it's
not long enough if your mind is bent in
sensuality if your mind is bent on
comfort in avoiding pain so it is better
to live a shorter life with a greater
quality to it quality in terms of
practicing the dumb and dedication to us
that even if sometimes compromises your
health or exposes you to some risk you
don't do it foolish or crazily like in
destructors you don't go and stand in
front of mad elephant or something like
that but you certainly don't stay in a
in a little village village village
house because you know you might get
sick in the forest I mean you can stay
if you don't wanna practice I'm not sure
then while you monkey first place
again I'm coming from obviously the
Western point of view we were not
brought up with Buddhists because
sometimes people in Asian countries are
paying for traditional reasons act like
priests and stuff and that's absolutely
fine if that's what they do
but I'm talking about somebody who does
a Dane coming from a completely
different culture so it's absolutely no
traditional value for any of the
Westerners to be a Buddhist monk which
means they are dying out of some sort of
inspiration based on the Buddhist
teaching based on the suitors that they
read and so on so if you don't then
commit yourself to it and set yourself
and and expose yourself to some risks
for something well you were never gonna
learn you're never gonna learn sort of
follows until next the stamina swatters
energetic enough one was lazy here bhiku
has aroused energy for bending and
wholesome qualities and acquired posit
policies his strong firm an exertion not
casting as the duty of cultivating force
of qualities
dummies for one who's not doing becoming
a monk a tradition whatever you see or
something out of duty well I think that
might have been the case back in the day
yeah dumb ways for one yeah first and
obviously that's the reason one should
do it but I think today what isn't being
quite a major religion part of society I
think that many other reasons people
would attend that's why I mean I'm not
really talking about every single person
who wears robes but I'm like somebody
who did ordained for relatively
non-traditional reasons to practice the
Dharma and then doesn't practice it by
staying dependent on the crowd depending
on the establishment worrying about the
future worrying about what I'll do when
I get old if I can't climb the hill or
whatever else well instead of worrying
about that practice now because the
boots himself said many times practice
now while you can
otherwise it'll be too late because if
you practice now you won't be worried
about later
like the case was that's what Amaka
better month Passover where the Buddha
saw give me the forest to Birmingham
ground-living but in hard ascetic life
and said oh come on you finish your work
come and stay with me I get plenty of
offers of better dwellings year old you
don't need to do that painting him he
said well it's not painful because I've
done all the work my developer money
Janice can develop them and will
establish them in the world all this is
pure Georgian and who the crazy but say
there will be the inspiration for future
generations hearing that
so not advocating carelessness but I'm
not certain I'm not I'm not endorsing
cowardice is nothing careless about
seeking solitude but yeah it can be
quite a frightening thing even it it's
not like a physically dis tential threat
people would be afraid being alone not
having anything to do not having duties
dictating the day what I must do not
having other people telling them what to
do I mean it's the most frightening
thing for most people but for any other
night of mine and so no not
becoming a monk on one hand and they're
not dealing with it on the other well
it's a contradiction in terms
the somebody who's inspired to practice
Dhamma that's the ultimate thing you
need to deal with abandoning your own
sense of self and you cannot do that for
as long as you're in the crowd
depending on the crowd depending and
when I say crowd I don't mean you sit in
the middle of Times Square or something
I mean crowded with other monks
constantly with other lay people with
other people to stop